Do software fundamentals still matter?
Or is the programmer just dead as a
profession? Should we just ignore the
code and just focused on the outputs of
what the AI is producing? Just let it be
a black box. Well, I've got an idea for
you, which is that the code is the
environment the agent operates in and
the quality of the environment
influences the output of the agent
working in that code base. So, if you
have a garbage code base, then the agent
is going to produce garbage. And the
thing about garbage code bases is they
sneak up on you. So, there's a concept
called software entropy where unless
you're very careful about organizing the
code base, thinking strategically about
what you're doing, having a long-term
view of the code base, applying software
fundamentals, then the code base slowly
gets worse and worse, more disorganized,
harder to work in over time. And from
what I've seen so far of AI, humans are
a lot better at working in bad code
bases than AI is. Humans have memory and
so they can remember what works in a
code base and what doesn't. This isn't
perfect, of course, but it means that
they can develop a sense for a bad code
base over time and still remain
relatively productive in it. Agents have
no memory
unless you bolt on a kind of crappy
memory system onto them, which is a very
unsolved problem. They are kind of like
the guy from Memento that wakes up in
the code base and goes, "Okay, I'm
awake.
Uh what do I remember? Nothing." And so
you have to re-teach them everything
about this bad code base as it goes.
This means that AI will make the same
mistakes again and again in your code
base unless you're there thinking
strategically, working with guardrails,
getting them to where they need to be,
preventing their mistakes. This is true
of dumb models and it's true of smart
models. The problem is not the ability
to reason, it's the fact that these code
bases are hard to explore, hard to work
in, hard to make changes in, and it's
just a tricky environment for the AI to
work in. The people who are most
valuable right now are the ones who can
build great agent experiences in their
code base. And that comes from having
code that's easy to explore, having
tests that test at really good seams,
having good module design and interface
design. And so, yes, software
fundamentals still matter more than ever
because good code bases matter more than
ever.